Let's begin today today's uh morning
session. So we're going to go over
differential equations and plotting in
Julia. Uh these are both of these are
two concepts that are basically you know
the backbone of year blocks and in
particular we're going to talk about u
modeling toolkit and uh the maki
ecosystem. So and first things first
with uh modeling toolkit is um is a
modeling language within the scientific
machine learning ecosystem in Julia
um where you can uh write down systems
of differential equations in a symbolic
manner. It's a it's a very intuitive way
of running them. I showed you an example
of that yesterday when I was talking
when I was talking about how expressive
a Julia can be uh in its
syntax. And um then we'll go over Maki.
So Mike is a another ecosystem and by
ecosystem I mean essentially a
collection of packages that you know
work with each other and share some
common uh you know some some common
utilities and uh Mikey is one of the
alternatives you have if you want to
plot uh anything any data in Julia and
this is our go-to in yearblogs and uh I
will show you why and uh also yeah these
two things modeling toolkit and I go
well together and you will see that in
the examples uh
too. So starting with the with the
modeling toolkit as I as I mentioned it
is a part of the setting machine
learning ecosystem and here I just want
to show you um a graph basically of the
SML ecosystem because it's consisting of
a lot of packages. There's a lot going
on here. uh you can see modeling toolkit
uh on the right there and there is even
uh you know the differential equations
where it's a more programmatic way of
writing differential equations without
the nice symbolic syntax. Uh there are
packages to do partial differential
equations. These have to be specialized
because of the nature of those systems.
uh uncertainty
quantification um on your DBQ system and
there's even some newer utilities uh
like universal differential equations
and attaching a neural network inside
your equations to discover missing
terms. Uh but out of all this ecosystem
we will focus on modeling toolkit
because this will allow us to design new
blocks as well and this is how blocks in
neuroblocks are currently uh
designed. So this is uh an example from
the modeling toolkit u actually a course
on modeling toolkit that actually
highlights its modular design and uh
neuroblocks shares this value very much.
So here we have essentially want to
design a system that is a simple mass
and a dumper you know that uh a simple
mechanical system and let it oscillate.
Uh so first we design the mass as as a
as a system on its own right we write
down its variables and its equations
um and you know um add the component to
it which is a port and this port will
connect to the to the dumper. So moving
on uh the to the dumper definition
likewise we have the variables and the
equations and another port right and up
there on the on the right you can see
the definition of a port what that is
and eventually we we define another
model that is our system that brings
together our previous two models right
so you can see modern toolkit can be uh
very very modular and very very flexible
in its design and something similar is
going on in eurob blocks right we have
separate components and we can link them
together to to create a new component
like that system is right if you notice
that all of these components have this
uh at MTK model uh macro right so
they're all different models but some of
them like the final system contain other
models in them so similar to how in year
blocks we can have some blockes that
contain other blocks in them to have
this multiscale uh approach
And also this the SML ecosystem comes
with an extended solvers library. Uh
here you can see some examples uh from
the documentation of u of uh the yeah
the DQ docs in CML where basically uh
these are matches between some popular
solvers that people use in MLM and
Python or R and the equivalent uh solver
in Julia. So this helps you for instance
if you uh if you already have you know
your your model of differential
equations written in another language
it's easy to port it uh in Julia and
actually match your previous results to
make sure that you know the porting was
right because we have all these solvers
available and in fact we even have more
solvers available uh helmet touched on
this subject as well and on the on the
same page that I link up there in the
docs this is actually a very extensive
page that gives you recommendations
about which solver to use at what
situation. It goes over, you know,
stiffness, different levels of
stiffness, uh your the tolerance that
you're asking for, uh everything really.
It's it's very extensive. So, it's uh
yeah, the the solvers are very well
supported and documented in
SML and also again this is a reminder of
the of the performance that these
solvers can exhibit. Uh helmet also
showed you a slide like this. Here we
have uh two systems. The lot cavalera
system on top is a simple uh two
dimensional system that is not stiff and
the higher system is uh eight
differential equations but it's also uh
has a a stiff nature. So if you if you
notice more closely the the solvers that
we use in each case are different but
the color coding is the same and it's
split between languages and you can see
that in both of these cases uh Julia is
the fastest for any given error level
especially when we you know when we when
we reduce the error uh by a lot in uh
yeah in both of these cases. So our
solvers can be uh very
performant uh compared to other
languages. And also today I touched on
the subject of you know emergent
features in Julia where you know you can
have packages that have not been
designed together. They're not even part
of the same ecosystem but it just so
happens because of Julia's design that
they they can actually collaborate with
each other with minimal effort. So uh
this is a story like this with modeling
toolkit and measurements. So modeling
toolkit is part of the SML ecosystem and
it's uh yeah we we've been through it.
It's a it's a it's a package to define
differential equation systems but
measurement.jl that's a package in the
Julia physics ecosystem. of completely
separate people developing it in
completely separate ecosystems and
measurements um is um is a package for
to to do uncertainty quantification and
measurements right so all these plus
minus signs these two right on the on
when we set a parameter or when we set
an initial condition here uh these come
from measurements right but now we add
them to variables that are relevant to
modeling toolkits and it just works uh
there was really a minimal extra effort
that took place in order to make this
work. Right? So we can bring these two
together and on the right here I show
you a result of u essentially these two
packages collaborating where when we
simulate this system which is a simple
exponential decay, right? If you were to
simulate it without the measurement
quant uncertification then then you
would only get a single line, right? A
single exponential decay. But because
you add these plus minus signs in both
the parameter value and the initial
condition then you have these bands uh
around your solution that is essentially
the same uncertainty propagated forward
uh to the integrator and to the final
solution. U moving on to Mikey. So as I
said Mikey is is an ecosystem in itself
uh about plotting and uh it comes with
uh four different backends. So Mikey is
there as as an interface you know it it
uh it sets all the plotting functions
but the actual rendering is happening uh
on the back end right and there are four
options for the back end there's kyro
Mikey which is the one that we're going
to use and the one that uh neuroblocks
is using internally uh for 2D graphics
that can be the publication quality uh
graphics uh there's gli the for uh GPU
powered 2D and 3D plots so if you have
something uh computationally very heavy
to plot
And you can you can explode your GPU and
use GL Mikey with this uh WGL Mikey
which is uh web based and it's also
interactive both in 2D and 3D and there
there is experimental package that is
being developed now that's RPR Mikey
that does rate tracing so for more
photorealistic uh graphics and I also
link beautiful.mmikey.org there because
I think it's a it's a it's a it's a very
good example of what Mikey can do. So if
you if you want to convince yourself to
use Mikey then go check that page and
see what uh actually one person that uh
that runs is what he's able to make in
Mikey. So you can see what's possible.
uh but also within the Mikey ecosystem
uh there is like um there there's the
extended ecosystem you know besides the
core functionality where people have
have uh used Mikey to make uh different
kinds of plots and of course these are
open source and part of the uh extended
ecosystem. So unfold Mikey very useful
for neuroscience. This is a package to
well that does all these plots that you
can see here if you know from power
spectrums
um even power spectrums map on the scalp
that you that you could use as NEG and
source localization and uh event related
potentials and then there's also per
plots where you can do uh essentially
these triangular plots of you know
combinations uh of different uh
correlations between your parameters.
uh Geom Mikey for geographical plots and
there's also multi multibody which is
about you know multi-body physics and
you can actually you know design robotic
arms like that or any body you know out
of uh out of boxes and have it animate
as well and this is only a subset if you
go to the Mikey to the Mikey website you
will see that the this extended
ecosystem uh is quite large there there
are way more examples uh in
And finally the I want to touch on Mikey
layouts because I think this is one of
the main features uh that makes Mikey uh
attractive to new users. It certainly
did it for me. Uh you will see it in in
today's exercise as well. It's it's very
easy to make layouts like this when you
have you know subloads and maybe some
subloads are split into more subloss.
For instance, panel A here. As you can
see, there are three plots there and a
legend. And it's very easy to organize
them in in a single square right next to
C, which is just an image of a brain.
And then the the other two plots again
with multiple subplots. Uh and if you
want to follow this layout example, uh
you can do this uh on the on the Mikey
on the Mikey website
uh on the layout tutorials basically.
And it's uh if you're coming from uh for
instance R and you know ggplot 2 which
is a different syntax it's using this
grammar of graphics syntax for designing
graphics. This is also possible in Mikey
uh by using this algebra of graphics uh
package. And also yeah I would say that
if you're coming from Python the syntax
in designing uh plots is looks more like
mattplot lib if you were to use you know
uh base Mikey without the algebra
graphics.
Um so yeah this is all for now and um in
terms of uh notebooks uh you can you can
navigate on the website as well we'll
cover the differential equations in
Julia section and the plotting with
Mikey section so please start with
differential equations in Julia again
you can see exactly the same material in
notebook or the website right uh so
please first use this introdq notebook
and when you're done with this the
differential equations part uh you can
navigate to the page the plot with mic
page and use the uh intro plot uh
notebook
uh and yeah do you have any questions on
the
presentation? Okay, if not then yeah
feel free to start with the notebooks
and ask us questions anytime. Yeah,
thank you.